JAMES BLAKE

Postgraduate Student (Research, full-time)

J.Blake@warwick.ac.uk

+44 7500 521149

in in/jamesblake95

♀ Coventry, United Kingdom



EXPERIENCE

Postgraduate Student (Research, full-time)

Sept 2017 - Ongoing

Popt. Physics, Uni. Warwick, UK

- Developing Python analysis pipelines to detect and characterise artificial debris in astronomical images of the geosynchronous region
- Astrodynamical simulations, orbital analysis and fitting

See my department webpage for further detail, including publications.

Senior Outreach and Recruitment Ambassador

March 2014 - Ongoing

- SROAS Office, Uni. Warwick, UK
- Mentoring and tutoring for several WP outreach programmes, including Sutton Scholars, Brilliant Club, UniTracks and Realising Opportunities
- Planning and delivering outreach sessions for year 7–13 students in schools
- Developing communication skills through campus tours, open days, calling

Summer Research Intern

2015, 2016 & 2017

P Dept. Physics, Uni. Warwick, UK

- Undertook three 10-week summer projects as part of the Undergraduate Research Support Scheme (URSS), in exoplanetary science and astrobiology
- Extensive use of Python for data analysis and/or modelling

Work Experience Placement

Aug - Sept 2012

♀ Laser 2000 Ltd, Huntingdon, UK

- Received training as a prospective Sales Engineer, covering the theory and commercialisation of photonic equipment
- Entrusted with digitization of legal documents, carried out a research project

HIGHLIGHTS

Additional roles | Secretary for GNOSIS (2019-); UG Lab Marker (2017-20); Sales Assistant, Blue Inc (2014–16); Maths Tutor, Barrs Hill School, Coventry (2014–15); Fundraiser, St John's Ambulance, Carmarthenshire (2014)

Leadership | Technical session co-Chair at AMOS Conference, Hawai'i, US (2020); Co-founder and Vice-President of Warwick Astronomy Society (2016); Academic Coordinator for Warwick Physics Society (2016)

Event Management | Organised and coordinated the GNOSIS Precision SSA Virtual Workshop (2020, 60+ attendees); Coordinating events for audiences of 200+ visitors on open days; Organising UG revision lectures

Teaching & Outreach | Demonstrating for Python programming workshops; Co-supervising UG project students; Leading revision lectures for several UG modules; Visiting schools with a portable planetarium, delivering immersive and educational shows; Leading sessions for year 7–13 pupils on summer schools, residentials and school visits, promoting STEM subjects

Communication | Presented at 10+ nat'l/int'l conferences; Invited to give 10+ talks/seminars at nat'l/int'l venues; Alumni Panellist for ICUR, streamed internationally (2020); Confident speaker, excellent customer service

Publications & Media | Multiple peer-reviewed articles and conference proceedings, 3 as first author; Multiple press releases reaching 100+ news outlets across the globe - see e.g. BBC interview; Writer for The Conversation

Awards | Best Student Paper, AMOS Conference, Hawai'i, US (2019); Best Poster, Posters in Parliament, London, UK (2018); Significant Contribution to Outreach Activities, SROAS Office, Uni. Warwick, UK (2016)

Courses | EMER-GEN, Hawai'i, US (2020), mentoring from space industry experts; ESA Space Debris Training Course, Transinne, BE (2019); Warwick Ventures Innovation to Impact, Uni. Warwick, UK (2019)

PROFILE

I am a final-year Ph.D. Student at Warwick University. My work has focused on the development of software tools to detect and characterise artificial debris in optical telescope

I am also passionate about outreach, and have been involved in numerous efforts to promote HE and STEM in local schools.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Space Science | Uni. Warwick, UK

Sept 2017 - Ongoing

Funding: Science & Technology Facilities Council

Supervisor: Don Pollacco

M.Phys. in Physics | Uni. Warwick, UK

m Sept 2013 - June 2017 Grade: First Class Honours

Key topics: Mechanics, Relativity, Quantum, Electricity & Magnetism, Materials, Computing,

Electronics, Astronomy

A Levels & GCSEs | Wrenn Sixth Form, UK

Sept 2010 - June 2013

A2: Maths (A*), Hist. (A*), Phys. (A), Chem. (A) AS: Above 4(A), Furth. Maths (A), Phil. (B) GCSE: 9(A*) incl. Maths, IT, Eng. Lang. & 5(A)

COMPUTING

github/jblake95 for projects

- Operating systems Linux, MacOS, Windows
- Programming languages Python, C, Bash
- Selected libraries

NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, astropy, astroquery, SEP, datetime, rebound, Skyfield, ellc, emcee, pandas, json

Software packages

IRAF, SAOImage DS9, AstroImageJ, Astrometry.net, Origin Pro, MASTER, DRAMA

- Developer tools Git, PyCharm, Geany, Spyder
- Word processing LETEX, Microsoft Office, Libre Office
- Common tasks

Data analysis, image reduction and processing, database querying, modelling, simulations

REFERENCES

Available on request.